Guide to the Henry Guerlac papers, 1922-1981
Guerlac, Henry papers, 1922-1981
- Series XVII: Lecture notes: Survey course in the history of science
  - 3. The Mesopotamian Civiliation (Box 13, Folder 34)
  - 4. Egyptian Civilization (Box 13, Folder 35)
  - Lecture II (Box 13, Folder 36)
  - Radio-Carbon Dating (Box 13, Folder 37)
  - Mind of Primitive Man (Box 13, Folder 38)
  - Lecture III (Box 13, Folder 39)
  - 5. Babylonian Number System and Math (Box 13, Folder 40)
  - 6. Babylonian Astronomy (Box 13, Folder 41)
  - 6. Origins of the Greek Peoples (Box 13, Folder 42)
  - 7. The Greek Natural Philosophers (Box 13, Folder 43)
  - Lecture IV (Box 13, Folder 44)
  - 9. Calendrical Astronomy (Box 13, Folder 45)
  - Mathematics before Plato (Box 13, Folder 46)
  - Rise of Athens--Plato VII (Box 13, Folder 47)
  - 8. Greek Medical Science (Box 13, Folder 48)
  - 9. The Socratic Revolt (Box 13, Folder 49)
  - 10. Greek Mathematics to the Time of Plato (Box 13, Folder 50)
  - Timaeus (Box 13, Folder 51)
  - 11. Greek Mathematics Continued (Box 13, Folder 52)
  - Aristotle X (Box 13, Folder 53)
  - 12. Aristotle (Box 13, Folder 54)
  - Lecture (Box 13, Folder 55)
  - 13. Aristotle Continued (Box 13, Folder 56)
  - 15. The Hellenistic War (Box 13, Folder 57)
  - 16. Math and Physical Science in Alexandria (Box 13, Folder 58)
  - 17. Revival of Atomism (Box 13, Folder 59)
  - 18. Astronomy and Geodetics (Box 13, Folder 60)
  - Early Greek Astronomy (Box 13, Folder 61)
  - Greek Science - Astronomy Lecture (Box 13, Folder 62)
  - 19. Mathematical Astronomy (Box 13, Folder 63)
  - 20. Hellenistic Biology and Medicine (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Greek Astrology (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - 21. Philosophical Fare of the Romans (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - 22. Declining Rome and Christianity (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - 23. Onset of the Dark Ages (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - 24. The Church Fathers (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - 26. Light in the East - Byzantium (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - 25. Light in the East - II. The Arabic Empire (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - 26. Alchemy and Arabic - Chemistry (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - 27. The Awakening of Europe - Bede (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - 28. Renaissance in the 12th Century (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - 29. Philosophy and Religion in the 13th Century (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - 30. The 13th Century - Medieval Century of Genius (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - 31. Roger Bacon and Experimental Science (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Medieval Technology (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Technology and Invention in the Middle Ages (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - The Rise of Mechanism in 14th Century, Natural Philosophy, Ernest Addison Moody (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - 32. The 14th Century - A Time of Troubles (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - 14th C. Medieval Dynamics and Kinematics XXII (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - 33. Age of Renaissance and Reformation (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - 34. The Influence of Humanism (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - 35. Discovery and Geography (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - 37. View of the 16th Century (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - 38. Rise of Modern Astronomy (Box 14, Folder 24)
  - 39. The Followers of Copernicus (Box 14, Folder 25)
  - 40. Johann Kepler, Scientific Mystic (1571-1630) (Box 14, Folder 26)
  - Some Experiments of Galileo (Box 14, Folder 27)
  - 41. Galileo and Copernicus (Box 14, Folder 28)
  - 42. Galileo - Founder of Classical Physics (Box 14, Folder 29)
  - 43. The New Learning (Box 14, Folder 30)
  - 47. Developments in Medicine and Surgery (Box 14, Folder 31)
  - 49. Harvey and the Circulation of Blood (Box 14, Folder 32)
  - 51. The Assault on Aristotelian Physics, II - Studies on Sound and Light (Box 14, Folder 33)
  - Newton (Box 14, Folder 34)
  - 53. The Assault on Aristotelian Physics, III - Newtonian Dynamics (Box 14, Folder 35)
  - 55. Some Mathematical Developments of the16th and 17th Centuries (Box 14, Folder 36)
  - 57. Newton's Scientific Legacy (Box 14, Folder 37)
  - 58. Experimental Science in the 18th Century (Box 14, Folder 38)
  - 59. Matter and Its Transformation (Box 14, Folder 39)
  - 60. Lavoisier and the Chemical Revolution (Box 14, Folder 40)
  - 61. History, Natural History and Evolution (Box 14, Folder 41)
  - 69. Heat and Thermodynamics (Box 14, Folder 42)
  - Natural Religion, Deism and Physics, Theology (Box 14, Folder 43)
  - 73. Birth of Scientific Biology, II--The Behavior of Living Matter (Box 14, Folder 44)
  - 77. Darwin and Evolution (Box 14, Folder 45)
  - 79. The Scientific Study of Man, I--History and Archaeology (Box 14, Folder 46)
  - 16th Century--XXXIII (Box 14, Folder 47)
  - Chemistry in the 19th Century (Box 14, Folder 48)
  - "Some Aspects of Science"--reprint (Box 14, Folder 49)
- Series XVIII: 17th and 18th century material for articles in progress
  - Bentley and Newton (Box 14, Folder 50)
  - John Haris on Aether: Vacuum and Gravity (Box 14, Folder 51)
  - Huygens (Box 14, Folder 52)
  - Leibniz (Box 14, Folder 53)
  - Malebranche (Box 14, Folder 54)
  - Malebranche and Malebranchistes (Box 14, Folder 55)
  - Mouy on "Malebranche et Newton" (Box 14, Folder 56)
  - Pardies (Box 14, Folder 57)
  - Sprat, Thomas (Box 14, Folder 58)
  - Varignon Letters to Newton (Box 14, Folder 59)
  - John Wallis's Autobiography (Box 14, Folder 60)
  - Christopher Wren (Box 14, Folder 61)
  - Newton in France (Box 14, Folder 62)
  - Cheyne, George and Newton (Box 14, Folder 63)
  - De Moivre and Newton (Box 14, Folder 64)
  - Desaguliers to Hans Sloane (Box 14, Folder 65)
  - Desaguliers on Newton's Method (Box 14, Folder 66)
  - Desaguliers: Newtonian System (Box 14, Folder 67)
  - David Gregory: Preface to His Astronomy (Box 14, Folder 68)
  - Hawksbee and Desaguliers - Experiments (Box 14, Folder 69)
  - Hawksbee - Notes for Revision (Box 14, Folder 70)
  - Hawksbee's Experiments and Hook and Papin (Box 14, Folder 71)
  - Hawksbee and Journal Book (Box 14, Folder 72)
  - Hawksbee - Papers in Philosophical Transactions (Box 14, Folder 73)
  - Hawksbee, Electricity and Newton's Opticks (Box 14, Folder 74)
  - John Keill - Divisibility of Matter (Box 14, Folder 75)
  - John Keill on Attraction (Box 14, Folder 76)
  - Poliniere, Pierre de (Box 14, Folder 77)
  - Polignac, Cardinal de (Box 14, Folder 78)
  - Polignac, Faucher on (Box 14, Folder 79)
  - Newton and Pope (Box 14, Folder 80)
  - Sigorgne (Box 14, Folder 81)
  - 18th Century Commentators (Box 14, Folder 82)
  - Bibliography Enlightenment (1660-1803) (Box 14, Folder 83-84)
  - 17th Century Lectures (Box 14, Folder 85)
  - 17th Century Alphabetical Notes (Box 14, Folder 86-87)
  - 17th Century Alphabetical Notes (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
  - Amicus Plato--notes and draft (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - 9. Berthelot (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Lavoisier and Laplace (Box 15, Folder 5-6)
  - Laplace's Collaboration with Lavoisier (draft of Paris paper), 1968 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Laplace and Probability (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Gene Frankel on Laplace (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Lavoisier--Laplace (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - G. Moll on Laplace (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Laplace--Biographical Articles on His Youth (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Laplace (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - "Laplace as a Newtonian Scientist" by Roger Hahn (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Laplace and Lavoisier - Notes from O.L. II, p. 262-272 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Lavoisier and Volta (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Magellan in Rozieri Journal (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Brissan-- Dictionnaire de Physique article, "Feu" (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Macquer, Dictionnaire, 2nd ed. ( 1778 ) article "Feu" (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - "De l'elasticité et de la Formation des Fluides Elastiques" (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - Chabrol - Letter of Lavoisier to Trudaine de Montigny, 1777 (Box 15, Folder 21)
  - Lavoisier Explanation of Vaporization (Box 15, Folder 22)
  - Brisson--Dictionnaire de Physique, ed. I ( 1780 ) (Box 15, Folder 23)
  - 18th Century Theories of Heat (Box 15, Folder 24)
  - Conceptions de Lavoisier - Affinités (Box 15, Folder 25)
  - Lavoisier "De la Combinaison.. ." (Box 15, Folder 26)
  - Revolution in Physics - Fermentation (Box 15, Folder 27)
  - Fermentation (Box 15, Folder 28)
  - Cusa, Vitruvius and Number - Cusa and Pythagoreanism (Box 15, Folder 29)
  - Vitruvius (Box 15, Folder 30-31)
  - Cusa, Nicolas (Box 15, Folder 32)
  - Numbers and Numerology in the Middle Ages (Box 15, Folder 33)
  - Cusa's De Staticis and Of Learned Ignorance (Box 15, Folder 34)
  - Debus: Math in Chemical Texts of Renaissance (Box 15, Folder 35)
  - Uzielli on Toscanelli (notes from Yale copy) (Box 15, Folder 36)
  - Hellenistic Metrical Number (Box 15, Folder 37)
  - Greek ideas re number (Box 15, Folder 38)
  - Santorio, Santorio and "Statics" (Box 15, Folder 39)
  - Metaphysical and Metric Number (Box 15, Folder 40)
  - Greek Math - Pythagoreanism (Box 15, Folder 41)
  - John Dee and Hermetism (Box 15, Folder 42)
  - Hermetic Philosophy (Box 15, Folder 43)
  - Oronce Fine's Preface to His Protomathesi (Box 15, Folder 44)
  - Anatomy of Vandalism (Box 15, Folder 45)
  - 17th Century: Franklin--Biographical Outline (Box 15, Folder 46)
  - Benjamin Franklin Manuscript (Box 15, Folder 47-48)
  - Claude Lopez on Franklin (Box 15, Folder 49)
  - L. Labaree - Benjamin Franklin's British Friendships (Box 15, Folder 50)
  - Franklin and the French Scientists (Box 15, Folder 51-52)
  - Franklin and Lavoisier (Box 15, Folder 53)
  - The Papers of Benjamin Franklin, William B. Willcox, editor (Box 15, Folder 54)
  - Club of Honest Whigs - Letters of B. Rush to Franklin (Box 15, Folder 55)
  - Franklin on Heat and Aurora (Box 15, Folder 56)
  - Barbeu-Barbeu and Franklin (Box 15, Folder 57)
  - Franklin's French associates--Early years--Lavoisier (Box 15, Folder 58)
  - Franklin and Ingenhousz (Box 15, Folder 59)
  - Chinard on "Affaires le l'Angleterre et de l'Amerique" (Box 15, Folder 60)
  - American Philosophical Society Library (APSL), Letter: Lavoisier to Franklin, 8 June 1777 (Box 15, Folder 61)
  - APSL, Letter: Lavoisier to Franklin (Box 15, Folder 62)
  - APSL, Letter from Lavoisier to Franklin, 10 Nov. 1780 (Box 15, Folder 63)
  - APSL, Letter from Lavoisier to Franklin, 27 Jan. 1781 (Box 15, Folder 64)
  - Joseph Black on Franklin (Box 15, Folder 65)
  - Franklin in France (Box 15, Folder 66)
  - Franklin and American Philosophical Society (Box 15, Folder 67)
  - Franklin Letters and Publication (Box 15, Folder 68)
  - Franklin (Box 15, Folder 69)
  - Franklin - Bibliographical Notes and Chronology (Box 15, Folder 70)
  - Claude A. Lopez: "... addenda to the correspondence of Lavoisier and Franklin" (Box 15, Folder 71)
  - Lavoisier and Franklin (Box 15, Folder 72)
  - Benjamin Rush (Box 15, Folder 73)
  - Abbé Raynal (Box 15, Folder 74)
  - Method of Analysis in 17th Century (Box 15, Folder 75)
  - Jombert (Box 15, Folder 76)
  - 13. Jombert (Box 15, Folder 77)
  - French Printing: 18th Century and Revolution (Box 15, Folder 78)
- Series XIX: Newton files
  - Albury on Reception and Huygens (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Albury on Halley (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - William H. Austin - Newton and Religion (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - S.L. Bethel (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Newton Biography in Biographie Universelle (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Carl B. Boyer (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - David Brewster (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Brunet: Int de Newton en France (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Buchdahl on Hegel's Optics (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Clark, G.N., Science and Social Welfare in the Age of Newton (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Cohen: Newton Papers (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Cohen: Newton Papers (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - I.B. Cohen: Principia, The Scriptures and The Divine Providence (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Condillac - "Modern History" (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Dobbs, Betty Jo (Box 16, Folder 15-18)
  - Dictionary of Scientific Biography on Newton (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - Ellis, Newton's Concept of Motive Force (Box 16, Folder 20)
  - Figala, Karin (Box 16, Folder 21)
  - R.J. Forbes on Newton's Chemistry (Box 16, Folder 22)
  - Hall papers on Newton (Box 16, Folder 23)
  - Heimann, Peter (Box 16, Folder 24)
  - Hoskin (on Clarke's Notes to Rohault) (Box 16, Folder 25)
  - E.L. Huxley: "Two Newtonian Studies" (Box 16, Folder 26)
  - IBM Exhibit, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 27)
  - Jacob, James (Box 16, Folder 28)
  - Jacob, Margaret Candee (Box 16, Folder 29)
  - Peg Candee Jacob on Toland (Box 16, Folder 30)
  - Kubrin, David (Box 16, Folder 31)
  - Kargon, Robert, "Newton, Barrow and the Hypothetical Physics" (Box 16, Folder 32)
  - Jardine, Lisa (Box 16, Folder 33)
  - Philip E.B. Jourdine: Aether (Box 16, Folder 34)
  - Alexandre Koyre on Newton (Box 16, Folder 35)
  - Kubrin, David: Newton and the Development of the Cosmos, Providence and the Mechanical Philosophy (Box 16, Folder 36)
  - Lamprecht - Descartes in England (Box 16, Folder 37)
  - Leibniz and Newton (Box 16, Folder 38)
  - Mairan and Newton (Box 16, Folder 39)
  - Manuel, Frank (Box 16, Folder 40)
  - McMullin--"Newton's Concept of Matter" (Box 16, Folder 41)
  - Osler, Margaret on Descartes and Charleton (Box 16, Folder 42)
  - Phyllis McKenzie (student): 1969 paper on Newton (Box 16, Folder 43)
  - Munby, A.N.L. (Box 16, Folder 44)
  - Patterson, Louise Diehl (Box 16, Folder 45)
  - Pelseneer, Jean (Box 16, Folder 46)
  - Karl Popper on Newton and Kepler (Box 16, Folder 47)
  - William Shea on Galileo's atomism (Box 16, Folder 48)
  - Rodney, Hanson etc. on Newton (Box 16, Folder 49)
  - Russian Writings on Newton (Box 16, Folder 50)
  - Sabra (Box 16, Folder 51)
  - Eikoh Shimao (Box 16, Folder 52)
  - Shirras, Findlay (Box 16, Folder 53)
  - Strong: Newton and God (Box 16, Folder 54)
  - Sullivan's "Newton" - review of (Box 16, Folder 55)
  - Toulmin, Stephen (Box 16, Folder 56)
  - Westfall papers (Box 16, Folder 57)
  - Whiteside, Derek T. (Box 16, Folder 58)
  - W.D.P. Wightman on Newton's Opticks (Box 16, Folder 59)
  - Zeitlin, Jacob (Box 16, Folder 60)
  - Zilsel - "Copernicus and Mechanics" (Box 16, Folder 61)
  - Reviews (Box 16, Folder 62)
  - Laws of Nature (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - 18th Century Plan of the Mint (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Newton Book for Plumb Series - Outline (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - General Background - Political History (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Short Biography of Newton (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Newton - H.G. Research Notebook, May-June 1973 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Blake and Newton, etc. (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - J. Brown to Hans Sloane, 1731 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Bolingbroke (and Newton) (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Newton: Archival Resources (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Bibliography
    - A. Cappelli Chronologia and Stillman Drake's Letter (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Biography of Newton, draft, Summer, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Canon Foster: "Newton's Family" (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Lincolnshire (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Christopher Hatton Turnor--"The Countryside in Newton's Day" and History of Grantham (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Woolsthorpe, Grantham, Trinity (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - Cambridge (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - London (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Reliquiae Hearnianae (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - Cambridge in Newton's Day (Box 17, Folder 20-21)
    - Phyllis Allen: Science in 17th Century, English Universities (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - Audrade on Newton's reading (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - Royal Society (Box 17, Folder 24-26)
    - Joseph Spence - anecdotes (Box 17, Folder 27)
    - J.H. New Anecdotes of Sir Isaac Newton (Box 17, Folder 28)
    - Newton Notebook - Fitzwilliam Museum (Box 17, Folder 29)
    - I. D'Israeli - Curiosities of Literature (Box 17, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence re Newton (Box 17, Folder 31)
    - Newton's copy: Richard Baxter, The Nonconformist Plea for Peace (Box 17, Folder 32)
    - Newton's Death Mask (Box 17, Folder 33)
    - Library of Newton (Box 17, Folder 34)
    - Newton's Pendulum and the Aether (Box 17, Folder 35)
    - Newton's Ether Theory (Box 17, Folder 36)
  - Analysis
    - Newton and Analysis (Box 17, Folder 37-38)
    - Review inspired by Newton re Method (Box 17, Folder 39)
    - Randall - Scientific Method at Padua (Box 17, Folder 40)
    - J. Hintikka - Kant and Analysis (Box 17, Folder 41)
    - Lavoisier and Method of Analysis (Box 17, Folder 42)
    - Schmitt on Zabarella and Galileo (Box 17, Folder 43)
    - Analysis in Encyclopedie (Box 17, Folder 44)
  - Atomism
    - Gassendi's atomism (Box 17, Folder 45)
  - Cartesianism
    - Glauville on Descartes (Box 17, Folder 46)
    - Lamprecht on Cartesianism (Box 17, Folder 47)
  - Newton on chemistry
    - Chemistry in the 17th Century (Box 17, Folder 48)
    - Hartlib and Chemistry (Box 17, Folder 49)
    - Kenelm Digby's Chemistry (Box 17, Folder 50)
    - Chapter 1. Late eighteenth Century Newtonian Chemistry (Box 17, Folder 51)
    - Chapter 2. Late Eighteenth Century Lavoisier Chemistry (Box 17, Folder 52)
    - Draft notes on Newtonian Chemistry (Box 17, Folder 53)
    - Thackray--"Matter in a Nutshell" (Box 17, Folder 54)
    - Rattansi on Newton's Alchemy (Box 17, Folder 55)
    - Newton and Chemistry (Box 17, Folder 56)
    - Chait--Chemistry in the 31st Query (Box 17, Folder 57)
  - Chronology
    - Chronology (Box 17, Folder 58)
  - Newton on experiment
    - Experiment, Newton on (Box 17, Folder 59)
    - Newton's Experimentum Crucis (Box 17, Folder 60)
    - Thomas Sprat on Experiment (Box 17, Folder 61)
    - Force and Mass (Box 17, Folder 62)
  - Gravity
    - Newton's Theory of Gravitation (Box 17, Folder 63)
    - Newton and Gravitation (Box 17, Folder 64)
    - Publications on Gravity (Box 17, Folder 65)
  - Newton on hypotheses
    - 10th and 12th Century Math (Box 17, Folder 66)
    - Quantification (Box 17, Folder 67)
    - Mathematics (Box 17, Folder 68)
  - Theory of matter
    - John Harris--Woodward on Matter (Box 17, Folder 69)
    - Mechanical Philosophy (Box 17, Folder 70)
  - Newton on mechanics
    - Impact Theory of Newton (Box 17, Folder 71)
    - Music (Box 17, Folder 72)
  - The Opticks
    - Leibniz on Newton's theory of color (Box 17, Folder 73)
    - Principia (Box 17, Folder 74)
  - Qualities, intension and remission
    - Galileo on Intension and Remission (Box 17, Folder 75)
    - Qualities, Intension and Remission of (Box 17, Folder 76)
  - Newton on religion
    - Newton on Religion (Box 17, Folder 77)
    - Newton on Miracles (Box 17, Folder 78)
    - Natural Religion (Box 17, Folder 79)
  - 17th-Century figures
    - Auzout, Adrien (Box 17, Folder 80)
    - Borri, Francesco Giuseppe (Box 17, Folder 81)
    - Notes on Charlton (Box 17, Folder 82)
    - Cudworth, Ralph (Box 17, Folder 83)
    - Descartes (Box 17, Folder 84)
    - Hobbes, Thomas (Box 17, Folder 85-86)
    - Huygens, Christian (Box 17, Folder 87)
    - Mariotte (Box 17, Folder 88)
    - Mariotte and Huygens, - Academie Royale des Sciences, History (1666-1686) (Box 17, Folder 89)
    - More, Henry and Newton (Box 17, Folder 90)
- Series XX: Newton: Chemistry, Opticks
  - Chemistry in Opticks (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Rainbow (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Cotes, Roger--Hydrostatical and pneumatical lecture, 1738 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Crystallography (Schierbeck and Hooy Kaas) (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - De Dominis--De radii visus et Lucis (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Hooke--Micrographia (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Huygens--Abnormal height of a mercury column (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Lections optical (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - N. le Febure--on H2SO4 per campanam (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Lignum Nephriticum (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Newton and Mathematics (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Molyneux (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Lectiones Opticae (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - The Number Seven (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - Oculus Mundi (Box 18, Folder 15-16)
  - Orpheus (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - Principia II, 1713 (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - Nature of Heat (Box 18, Folder 19)
  - 17th Century Telescopes (Box 18, Folder 20)
  - Effluvia Theory, Gilbert - Brown - Newton (Box 18, Folder 21)
  - David Lindberg (Box 18, Folder 22-23)
  - Newton's Vocabulary (Box 18, Folder 24)
  - Oldenburg Correspondence--Comet of 1664 (Box 18, Folder 25)
  - Chronicle of Newton on Light (1671-1672) (Box 18, Folder 26)
  - Flamsteed Letters (Box 18, Folder 27)
  - Mairan in reply to Hortsoeker (Box 18, Folder 28)
  - Opticks--Miscellaneous notes (Box 18, Folder 29)
  - Life of Doctor John North (Newton's contemporary at Trinity) (Box 18, Folder 30)
  - John Biddle on Locke and Newton, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 31)
  - Sensorium (Box 18, Folder 32)
  - Changes in Queries of Optics (Box 18, Folder 33)
  - History of color
    - Lomonosov--"A Discourse on the Solidity and Fluidity of Bodies" (Box 18, Folder 34)
    - The Early Development of Science--Henry Guerlac (Box 18, Folder 35-37)
    - Robert Boyle and Structural Chemistry--Thomas Kuhn (Box 18, Folder 38)
    - Traite de Physique (Box 18, Folder 39)
    - Essay on Newton and Opticks (Box 18, Folder 40-43)
    - Notes for Introduction (Box 18, Folder 44-46)
    - Philosophical Transactions--Index (Box 18, Folder 47)
    - Index to Birch (Box 18, Folder 48)
    - Encyclopedie Methodique--Index (Box 18, Folder 49)
    - Thermometre Universel De Comparaison (Box 18, Folder 50)
    - Opticks Exhibit--Spring, 1966 (Box 18, Folder 51)
  - Correspondence: Opticks projects, etc.
    - Roy Bishop - Acadia University (rainbow) (Box 18, Folder 52)
    - Cambridge University Library and Trinity (Box 18, Folder 53)
    - Correspondence re: Opticks (Box 18, Folder 54)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence re: Opticks (Box 18, Folder 55)
    - Guggenheim report on Opticks project (Box 18, Folder 56)
    - Shimao (Box 18, Folder 57)
    - Solis (Box 18, Folder 58)
    - Henry Y.K. Tom (Box 18, Folder 59)
    - Westfall, personal (Box 18, Folder 60)
  - Editorial procedures
    - Introduction (Box 18, Folder 61)
    - Bower's record book, from Bodleian (Box 18, Folder 62)
    - Critical Edition of Opticks (Box 18, Folder 63)
    - Correspondence with publishers (Box 18, Folder 64)
    - Outline of Edition (Box 18, Folder 65)
    - Yale Photo Services (Box 18, Folder 66)
    - Newton's Opticks - Apparatus criticus and pagination (Box 18, Folder 67)
- Series XXI: Editing and publishing
  - Printing of Opticks
    - Press figures of Ed. II, Ed. III and Ed. IV, 1717-1718 (Box 18, Folder 68)
    - Term Catalogues (Box 18, Folder 69)
    - Moxon's Art of Printing and Printer's Grammar, 1683-1684, 1755 (Box 18, Folder 70)
    - Plates for E-04 (Box 18, Folder 71)
    - Cornell Press (Box 18, Folder 72)
  - Material for introduction
    - Maslen re Newton's Printer (Box 18, Folder 73)
    - Material for Introduction (Box 18, Folder 74)
    - Editor's Preface--Draft (Box 18, Folder 75-78)
    - Introduction--Miscellaneous sheets (Box 18, Folder 79)
    - Newton's First Optical Work (Box 18, Folder 80)
    - Abbreviations (draft) (Box 18, Folder 81)
    - Abbreviations of Works Cited (Box 18, Folder 82)
    - Abbreviations, final version (Box 18, Folder 83)
    - Explanations for my Editor (Box 18, Folder 84)
    - Editor's Preface and Notes (finished) (Box 18, Folder 85)
    - Editor's Preface - final (Box 18, Folder 86)
    - Influence of the Opticks in 18th Century (Box 18, Folder 87)
    - Writing and Publishing of the Opticks (Box 18, Folder 88)
    - Writing and Publishing of the Opticks (Box 18, Folder 89)
  - Newton manuscript
    - Manuscript Add. 3996 (Box 18, Folder 90)
    - Manuscript Add. 3975 (Box 18, Folder 91)
    - Manuscripts in Cambridge (Box 18, Folder 92)
    - Supposed Plan of Book IV (Box 18, Folder 93)
    - Newton and Mercury - his mental illness (Box 18, Folder 94)
    - Lectiones Opticae (Box 18, Folder 95)
    - French translation: 1720 and 1722 collations, 1720, 1722 (Box 18, Folder 96)
  - Modern translations
    - Mamiani translation (Box 18, Folder 97-99)
- Series XXII: Newton and Boscovitch
  - Draft--Newton paper for Hopkins (Box 18, Folder 100)
  - When and How was Newton's Opticks Written (Box 18, Folder 101)
  - Illustration for French edition of, 1722 (Box 18, Folder 102)
  - Pogo and Vavilov translation of Opticks (Box 18, Folder 103)